Do you feel this way?
你有過這種感覺嗎？
When you communicate with AI,
當你與 AI 溝通時，
you often feel like you are talking to a wall.
你經常會感覺像在對著一面牆說話。
Today, we will talk about how to master the art of cooperation with deep AI
今天，我們將討論如何掌握與深度 AI 合作的藝術
so that you can really get the result you want in your heart.
這樣你就能真正獲得你內心想要的結果。
OK, let's cut into a painful point that many people have encountered.
好的，讓我們切入許多人都遇到過的一個痛點。
When you are using AI tools, you don't know why you will be stuck.
當你使用 AI 工具時，你不知道為什麼會卡住。
You see, everyone should not be unfamiliar with this kind of picture.
你看，每個人都不應該對這種圖像陌生。
This is not just a cold technical error message.
這不僅僅是一個冷冰冰的技術錯誤信息。
I think it's more like a metaphor
我認為它更像是一個隱喻
that perfectly describes the feeling of failure of communication with AI.
完美描述了與 AI 溝通失敗的感覺。
You clearly know what you want,
你清楚地知道你想要什麼，
but AI can't get to your point.
但 AI 無法理解你的意思。
The sense of failure is just like the error message on the screen.
失敗感就像屏幕上的錯誤信息一樣。
It tells you directly that our communication is cut off.
它直接告訴你我們的溝通已經中斷。
That's right, this unconnected line is the core problem we have to solve today.
沒錯，這條未連接的線是我們今天必須解決的核心問題。
How do we break away from this kind of communication gap?
我們如何擺脫這種溝通障礙？
Don't worry, the good news is that there is really a system that can help us push this wall.
別擔心，好消息是確實有一個系統可以幫助我們推倒這面牆。
This solution does not require you to learn more complex and difficult instructions.
這個解決方案不需要你學習更複雜、更困難的指令。
It is actually a process, a concept called DD loop.
它實際上是一個流程，一個稱為 DD 循環的概念。
Its core spirit is to communicate with AI, not to finish the instructions and be fine.
它的核心精神是與 AI 溝通，不是完成指令就沒事了。
It is a process of coming back and forth.
它是一個來回往復的過程。
You first describe what you want as clearly as possible.
你首先盡可能清楚地描述你想要的東西。
AI will give you a result.
AI 會給你一個結果。
Then you have to play your judgment to identify the good and bad of this result.
然後你必須發揮判斷力來識別這個結果的好壞。
Finally, adjust your description at the beginning according to your identification.
最後，根據你的判斷調整你最初的描述。
You see, this is a loop.
你看，這就是一個循環。
So the goal of this loop is not just for AI to spit out a good answer.
所以這個循環的目標不僅僅是讓 AI 給出一個好答案。
The real goal is to create some results that you can't even imagine by working with AI.
真正的目標是通過與 AI 合作創造一些你甚至無法想像的結果。
This is the most powerful place.
這是最強大的地方。
How does this loop work?
這個循環是如何運作的？
Let's break it into two parts.
讓我們將其分為兩部分。
The first half is your description of AI.
第一部分是你對 AI 的描述。
The second half is your identification of AI's output.
第二部分是你對 AI 輸出的識別。
Whether it's description or identification,
無論是描述還是識別，
there are three key core elements to do them well.
都有三個關鍵核心要素需要做好。
Let's call it three P.
我們稱之為三個 P。
OK, let's look at the first part, the art of description.
好的，讓我們看看第一部分，描述的藝術。
That is to say, how to talk to AI at the beginning to make your needs clear.
也就是說，如何在一開始與 AI 交談以使你的需求清楚。
This is really more important than you think, 100 times more important than you think.
這確實比你想的要重要得多，重要 100 倍。
OK, three P, the first P is product, which is output.
好的，三個 P，第一個 P 是產品，也就是輸出。
The point here is to be specific, specific, specific.
這裡的要點是要具體、具體、再具體。
You can't just tell him to write an article for me.
你不能只是告訴它為我寫一篇文章。
It's too vague.
這太模糊了。
You have to tell him what the format of this article is.
你必須告訴它這篇文章的格式是什麼。
Is it a blog article or an official report?
是部落格文章還是正式報告？
Is the style lively and interesting or serious and professional?
風格是生動有趣還是嚴肅專業的？
How many words are the length?
長度有多少字？
How deep are the details?
細節有多深入？
Make these clear.
把這些說清楚。
Next, the second P, process, which is the process.
接下來，第二個 P，過程，也就是流程。
This is super cool.
這非常酷。
You don't just tell AI what you want.
你不只是告訴 AI 你想要什麼。
You can also guide him how to do it.
你也可以引導它如何去做。
It's like you're teaching him to think.
就像你在教它如何思考。
For example, you can ask him to do market analysis first.
例如，你可以先要求它進行市場分析。
Find three main groups of customers.
找出三個主要客戶群體。
Finally, make marketing suggestions for each group.
最後，為每個群體提出行銷建議。
Give him a framework, a step.
給它一個框架、一個步驟。
The quality of the result will be much better.
結果的品質會好得多。
Okay, the third P, performance.
好的，第三個 P，表現。
This is more like setting AI's personality.
這更像是設定 AI 的人設。
What kind of attitude do you want him to cooperate with you?
你希望它用什麼態度與你合作？
Do you want him to talk about the essence or the long story?
你希望它講要點還是長篇大論？
Do you want him to challenge your ideas like a strict coach?
你希望它像嚴格的教練一樣挑戰你的想法嗎？
Or like a gentle partner who keeps encouraging you and supporting you?
還是像溫柔的夥伴，不斷鼓勵和支持你？
You can set these.
你可以設定這些。
Okay, I've finished the first half of the description.
好的，我已經完成了描述的前半部分。
When you use these three P to clarify the needs,
當你用這三個 P 來澄清需求時，
AI will give you his answer.
AI 會給你它的答案。
Next, let's move on to the second half of our cycle.
接下來，讓我們進入循環的第二部分。
It's also a very important step.
這也是一個非常重要的步驟。
The skill of identification.
識別的技能。
The skill of identification is actually
識別的技能實際上是
to use the three P you just described
用你剛才描述的三個 P
as a check list.
作為檢查清單。
So first, identification output.
所以首先，識別輸出。
Look back.
往回看。
Did he give you the right format?
它給你的格式對嗎？
Is the style what you want?
風格是你想要的嗎？
Is the length in line with the requirements?
長度是否符合要求？
These things need to be checked one by one.
這些事項需要逐一檢查。
Next, identification process.
接下來，識別過程。
This is very important.
這非常重要。
Don't just look at the final answer.
不要只看最終答案。
You have to think about how AI got this answer.
你必須思考 AI 是如何得出這個答案的。
Did he follow the steps you gave him step by step?
它是否按照你給它的步驟一步步進行？
Do you think the analysis method he used is reasonable?
你認為它使用的分析方法合理嗎？
If the process is wrong,
如果過程有誤，
even if the result looks like it's okay,
即使結果看起來沒問題，
there may be blind spots that you can't see.
也可能存在你看不到的盲點。
Finally, identification performance.
最後，識別性能。
This is very intuitive.
這非常直觀。
Just feel your cooperation experience.
只需感受你與它的合作體驗。
Do you think the AI way of talking to you is helpful?
你認為 AI 與你交流的方式有幫助嗎？
Will it be too talkative or a bit out of the question?
它是否過於冗長或偏離主題？
If it feels wrong, it's okay.
如果感覺不對，沒關係。
This is where you can adjust the next time you describe it.
這是你下次描述時可以調整的地方。
So when you put the description and identification
所以當你把描述和識別
and their three P together,
以及它們的三個 P 結合在一起時，
you get a super powerful new ability.
你就獲得了一種超強大的新能力。
Let's go through a complete process.
讓我們走過一個完整的過程。
The first step is to use three P to produce process performance
第一步是使用三個 P 來產生過程性能
to clearly describe your needs.
來清楚地描述你的需求。
The second step, after the AI gives you something,
第二步，在 AI 給你東西之後，
you use the same three P to identify its quality.
你使用相同的三個 P 來識別它的品質。
The third step,
第三步，
based on your identification result,
根據你的識別結果，
give it feedback to correct the description at the beginning.
給它反饋以修正最初的描述。
This brings out the most important step four.
這引出了最重要的第四步。
Add you in.
加入你自己。
Your expertise, your experience, your judgment.
你的專業知識、你的經驗、你的判斷。
Remember,
記住，
AI is just your secondary driver.
AI 只是你的副駕駛。
The steering wheel is still in your hands.
方向盤仍然掌握在你的手中。
So did you find it?
那麼你發現了嗎？
What we're talking about today
我們今天談論的
is far beyond the so-called singing or system engineering.
遠超所謂的唱歌或系統工程。
This is actually training a new kind of critical thinking.
這實際上是在訓練一種新型的批判性思維。
What you're learning is how to work with a completely different intelligent body,
你正在學習的是如何與一個完全不同的智慧體合作，
how to guide it, evaluate it, and create value with it.
如何引導它、評估它，以及用它創造價值。
This is a necessary ability in the future.
這是未來必須具備的能力。
Before we end,
在我們結束之前，
I want to leave a question for everyone to think about.
我想留一個問題給大家思考。
For you,
對你而言，
in the whole D-D cycle,
在整個人-AI 循環中，
which level do you think is more challenging for you?
你認為哪個環節對你更具挑戰性？
Is it the front that needs to figure out how to describe the thoughts in your mind
是前端需要想辦法描述你心中的想法，
or the back that needs to accurately identify
還是後端需要準確判斷
whether what AI gives you is good or not?
AI 給你的答案是否好或不好？
There is no standard answer to this question.
這個問題沒有標準答案。
But if you figure it out,
但如果你想清楚了，
you may find the key to your future training,
你可能會找到你未來訓練的鑰匙，
which is also the starting point for you to truly master this superpower.
這也是你真正掌握這項超能力的起點。